A Guide to the Gubernatorial Appointments of the Virginia Secretary of Commonwealth, 1998-2014
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Gubernatorial Appointments of the Virginia Secretary of Commonwealth, 1998-2014
The Library of Virginia
52903
6.3 cu.ft. (18 boxes)
Virginia. Office of the Secretary of Commonwealth
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The folders must be reviewed before being served. Privacy protected information is considered closed for 75 years after date of record creation per Code of Virginia 42.1-78. Types of records restricted include, but are not limited to: forms with social security numbers and birth dates.
Acquisition Information
Transferred on 6 December 2019 by the Office of the Secretary of the Commonwealth, 1111 East Broad Street, 4th Floor, Richmond, Virginia, 23219.
Historical Information
The Office of the Secretary of the Commonwealth has evolved from early colonial times when there existed a Secretary of the Colony. Thomas Nelson held the position of the first Secretary of Virginia in 1776. Early Secretaries were elected by the public. An Act of the General Assembly in 1920 changed the election to a joint vote of the General Assembly. In a 1930 Act the duties of the Secretary were redefined with the Secretary of the Commonwealth serving as the ex officio secretary of the Governor, as custodian of many official State records, and as keeper of the Greater and Lesser Seals of the Commonwealth. The office of the Secretary has gradually acquired other functions, such as: service of out-of-state civil process; appointment and regulation of notaries public; and registration and oversight of lobbyists. The Office became a gubernatorial appointment subsequent to a 1958 Act of the Assembly. The Secretary of the Commonwealth is under the jurisdiction of the Governor's Office. The Secretary is appointed by the Governor for a term of four years. Currently the Secretary of the Commonwealth is responsible for gubernatorial appointments, clemency and restoration of civil rights requests and extraditions. Additional activities include: serving as ex officio Secretary to the Governor; serving as keeper of the seals of the Commonwealth; compiling and publishing the annual Blue Book; commissioning and regulating notary publics, including the publication of a Notary Handbook and conduct of disciplinary hearings; promulgating the lobbying disclosure requirements, registration of lobbyists, and recording of lobbying reports; servicing the civil process of out-of-state defendants and other parties; and authenticating and certifying the records of the courts and of any state agency.
Scope and Content
Gubernatorial appointments, 1998-2014, to state boards and commissions during the administrations of Governor James S. Gilmore (1998-2002), Governor Mark Warner (2002-2006), Governor Tim Kaine (2006-2010), and Governor Terry McAuliffe (2014-2018). Includes appointment sheets, correspondence, curriculum vitae and resumes, press releases, and financial disclosure statements.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I: Governor Gilmore, Governor Warner, and Governor Kaine Gubernatorial appointments, 1998-2010; and
Series II: Governor McAuliffe Gubernatorial appointments, 2014
Contents List
- Series I: Governor Gilmore, Governor Warner, and Governor Kaine Gubernatorial Appointments, 1998-2010, Extent: 5 cu. ft. (14 and 1/2 boxes). (Box 1-15)
  This series contains gubernatorial appointments, 1998-2010, to state boards and commissions by Governor Gilmore, Governor Warner, and Governor Kaine. Included are appointment sheets, correspondence, curriculum vitae and resumes, and press releases.
  Arranged by name of state board or commission.
  - Board of Rehabilitative Services, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - State Rehabilitation Advisory Council, 2003-2005 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Alzheimers Disease and Related Disorders Commission, 2002-2005 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Board of Health Professions, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Radiation Advisory Board, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Secure Panel Initiative, 2002-2005 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Board for the Blind and Vision Impaired, 2004-2005 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - State Certified Seed Board, 2000-2003 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Board of Trustees of the Roanoke Higher Education Authority, 2002-2005 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Virginia Parole Board, 2002-2005 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Board of Juvenile Justice, 2003-2005 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Advisory Committee on Juvenile Justice, 2001-2005 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Forensic Science Board, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Virginia Fire Service Board, 2000-2005 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Clinical Justice Services Board, 1999-2009 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - State Board of Corrections, 2002-2005 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Virginia Recycling Markets Development Council, 2001-2008 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Virginia Natural Resources Foundation Board of Trustees, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Virginia Workforce Council, 1999-2004 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Board for Waste Management Facility Operators, 2002-2005 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Board of Trustees for Chippokes Farm Plantation Foundation, 1998-2006 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Council on Indians, 1998-2003 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Potomac River Fisheries Commission, 2003-2004 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Small Business Environmental Compliance Advisory Board, 2001-2004 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Chesapeake Bay Local Assistance Board, 1998-2003 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Rail Advisory Board, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Transportation Safety Board, 1998-2005 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - State Hazardous Materials Emergency Response Advisory Council, 2000-2003 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Medal of Valor Review Board, 2002-2005 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Board of Correctional Education, 1998-2005 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Board of Commissioners, Virginia Port Authority, 1999-2005 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - United Nations Day, 1998-2005 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Board of Tourism Train Development Authority, 2003-2004 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Board of Accounting, 2002-2005 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Metropolitan Washington Airports Authority, 2002-2005 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Delmarva Advisory Board, 2002-2004 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Purchases and Supply Procurement Appeals Board, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Virginia Advanced Shipbuilding and Carrier Integration Center Board, 2002-2004 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Migrant and Seasonal Farmworkers Board, 2002-2005 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Joint Leadership Council of Veterans Service Organizations, 2003-2005 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Board for Opticians, 2002-2005 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Virginia Council on Human Rights, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Virginia Council on Human Resources, 2003-2005 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Child Day-Care Council, 2002-2005 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Board of Directors, Virginia National Defense Industrial Authority, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Board of Trustees to the Museum of Natural History, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Board of Trustees to the Virginia Museum of Natural History, 1998-2005 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Board of Directors of the Virginia Small Business Financing Authority, 1999-2005 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Southern Institute on Children and Families Task Force, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Virginia Military Advisory Council, 2002-2004 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Southern States Energy Board, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Northern Virginia Transportation Authority, 2000-2002 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Scientific and Technical Advisory Committee to the Chesapeake Executive Council, 1998-2002 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Board for the Virginia College Savings Plan, 2003-2005 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Southern Growth Policies Board, 1998-2005 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Southern Community Council, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Board of Dentistry, 2002-2005 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Board of Counseling, 2002-2005 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Advisory Board for the Virginia Department for the Deaf and Hard of Hearing, 2002-2004 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - State Emergency Medical Services Advisory Board, 2002-2005 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Virginia Board for People with Disabilities, 2002-2005 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Board of Trustees for the Family and Children's Trust Fund, 2002-2004 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - State Board for Community Colleges, 2002-2005 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Board of Education, 2002-2005 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Board of Trustees of the Frontier Culture Museum of Virginia, 2002-2005 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Board of Visitors, George Mason University, 2002-2005 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Commission for the Arts, 2002-2004 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Board of Visitors, Norfolk State University, 2003-2005 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Board of Trustees, A.L. Philpott Manufacturing Extension Partnership, 2002-2005 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Board of Visitors, Christopher Newport University, 2002-2005 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Commonwealth Council on Aging, 2002-2005 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Advisory Board on Acupuncture, 2002-2005 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Child Support Guideline Review Panel, 2005 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - State Child Fatality Review Team, 2004 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Board of Audiology and Speech Language-Pathology, 2002-2005 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Advisory Board on Athletic Training, 2002-2003 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Board of Directors, Assistive Technology Loan Fund Authority, 2002-2005 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Board of Visitors, Old Dominion University, 2002-2005 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Board of Visitors, University of Virginia and Affiliated Schools, 2002-2005 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Board of Trustees, Southwest Higher Education Center, 2002-2005 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Board of Visitors, University of Mary Washington, 2002-2005 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Board of Trustees, Science Museum of Virginia, 2002-2005 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Board of Visitors, Longwood University, 2002-2005 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - The Library Board, 2002-2005 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Board of Trustees, Virginia Museum of Fine Arts, 2002-2005 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Board of Trustees, Jamestown-Yorktown Foundation, 2002-2005 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Board of Visitors, James Madison University, 2002-2004 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Institute for Advanced Learning and Research, 2002-2005 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - State Historical Records Advisory Board, 2002-2005 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - State Council of Higher Education of Virginia, 2002-2005 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Virginia Water Resources Statewide Advisory Board, 2002-2003 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Board of Visitors, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, 2001-2005 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Board of Visitors, Virginia State University, 2001-2005 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Board of Visitors, Virginia Commonwealth University, 2002-2005 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Board of Visitors, Virginia Military Institute, 2002-2005, 2010 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Board of Visitors, Radford University, 2002-2005 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Board of Visitors, Gunston Hall, 2002-2005 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Board of Visitors, Gunston Hall, 2003 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Board of Health Professions, 2003-2004 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Board of Funeral Directors and Embalmers, 2003-2005 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Board of Trustees, Virginia Tobacco Settlement Foundation, 2002-2005 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Board of Long-Term Care Administrators, 2005 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Board of Medical Assistance Services, 2002-2006 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Board of Medicine, 2002-2005 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Military Aides-de-Camp, 2003-2004 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Virginia Foundation for the Humanities and Public Policy, 1998-2004 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Board of Optometry, 2002-2010 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Governor's Motorcycle Advisory Council, 2005-2006 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - P-16 Education Council, 2005 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Vocational Rehabilitation Council for the Blind, 2002-2005 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Advisory Board on Physician Assistants, 2002-2005 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Board of Physical Training, 2002-2005 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Board of Pharmacy, 2002-2005 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Board of Nursing, 2002-2005 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Virginia Irish Potato Board, 1998-2005 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Virginia Wine Board, 2004-2005 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Virginia Soybean Board, 1998-2005 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Special Advisory Commission on Mandated Health Insurance Benefits, 2002-2005 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Governor's Commission on Community and National Services, 1998-2005 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Governor's Commission on Community and National Services, 2002-2005 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Board of Psychology, 2002-2005 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Virginia Interagency Coordinating Council, 2002-2005 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Public Guardian and Conservator Advisory Board, 2002-2005 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Advisory Board on Respiratory Therapy, 1999-2002 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Advisory Board on Radiological Technology, 2002-2004 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Vocational Rehabilitation Council for the Blind, 2002-2004 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Advisory Board on Occupational Therapy, 2003-2005 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Board of Nursing Home Administrators, 2002-2004 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - State Executive Council for Comprehensive Services for At-Risk Youth and Families, 2002 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - State Health Department Sewage Handling and Disposal Appeal Reviews Board, 2004-2005 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Board of Social Work, 2001-2005 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Commonwealth Neurotrauma Initiative Advisory Board, 2004-2005 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Governor's Substance Abuse Services Council, 2002-2005 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Board of Veterinary Medicine, 2002-2003 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Advisory Board on Midwifery, 2005 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Scientific Advisory Board, 2005 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Board of Social Services, 2002-2005 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Board of Visitors, Christopher Newport University, 2002 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Board of Visitors, College of William and Mary, 2002-2005 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Board for Waterworks and Wastewater Works Operator, 2003-2005 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Latino Advisory Commission, 2003-2006 (Box 12, Folder 5-6)
  - Virginia Horse Industry Board, 2004-2005 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Board of Directors, Virginia Tourism Authority, 2002-2005 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Tobacco Indemnification and Community Revitalization Commission, 2002-2005 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - State Building Code Technical Review Board, 2004 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Small Business Advisory Board, 2002-2006 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Board for Barbers and Cosmetology, 2002-2006 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Safety and Health Codes Board, 2002-2005 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Real Estate Board, 2002-2005 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Board of Directors of the Virginia Resources Authority, 2003-2005 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Real Estate Appraiser Board, 2002-2005 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Board for Professional Soil Scientists and Wetland Professionals, 2004-2005 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Commission on Local Government, 2003-2005 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Tobacco Settlement Financing Corporation, 2003 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Secure Virginia Panel, 2003 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Virginia-Israel Advisory Board, 2004-2005 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Virginia Manufactured Housing Board, 2002-2005 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Board of Commissioners of the Virginia Housing Development Authority, 2002-2004 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Board for Professional and Occupational Regulation, 2002-2005 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Board of Housing and Community Development, 2002-2005 (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Virginia Gas and Oil Board, 2002-2005 (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Board for Hearing Aid Specialists, 2002-2005 (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Board of Directors of the Virginia Economic Development Partnership, 2002-2006 (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - Board for Contractors, 2000-2005 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Coal Surface Mining Reclamation Fund Advisory Board, 2002-2005 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Virginia Coal Mine Safety Board, 2003 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Center for Rural Virginia Board of Trustees, 2004 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Board for Mineral Mining Examiners, 2004 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Governor's Mined Land Reclamation Advisory Committee, 2003 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Board of Coal Mining Examiners, 2005 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Cemetery Board, 2002-2005 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Auctioneers Board, 2002-2005 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Board for Architects, Professional Engineers, Land Surveyors, Certified Interior Designers, and Landscape Architects, 2002-2005 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Virginia Board for Asbestos, Lead, and Home Inspectors, 2002-2005 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Apprenticeship Council, 2002-2005 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Virginia Small Grains Board, 2002-2005 (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Virginia Sheep Industry Board, 2004-2005 (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - Virginia Racing Commission, 2002-2005 (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - Virginia Pork Industry Board, 2002-2005 (Box 14, Folder 16)
  - Virginia Peanut Board, 2003-2005 (Box 14, Folder 17)
  - Milk Commissioner, 2002-2005 (Box 14, Folder 18)
  - Virginia Marine Products Board, 1999-2006 (Box 14, Folder 19)
  - Virginia Horse Industry Board, 2002-2005 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Board of Forestry, 2002-2004 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Virginia Egg Board, 1998-2006 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Virginia Cotton Board, 2002-2006 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Virginia Corn Board, 2003-2005 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Charitable Gaming Board, 2002-2005 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Virginia Cattle Industry Board, 2003-2005 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Aquaculture Advisory Board, 2002-2005 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Board of Agriculture and Consumer Affairs, 2002-2005 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Virginia Agricultural Council, 2002-2005 (Box 15, Folder 10)
- Series II: Governor McAuliffe, 2014, Extent: 1.3 cu. ft. (3 and 1/2 boxes). (Box 15-18)
  This series contains gubernatorial appointments, 2014, to state boards and commissions by Governor McAuliffe. Includes financial disclosure statements by persons appointed.
  Arranged by last name of person appointed.
  - A, 2014 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Ba-Be, 2014 (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Bi-By, 2014 (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - Ca-Co, 2014 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Co-Cu, 2014 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Da-Do, 2014 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Dr-Ev, 2014 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - F, 2014 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - G, 2014 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Ha, 2014 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - He-I, 2014 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - J, 2014 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - K, 2014 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - L, 2014 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Ma-Me, 2014 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Mi-Mu, 2014 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - N, 2014 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - O, 2014 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Pa-Po, 2014 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Pr-Q, 2014 (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Ra-Ro, 2014 (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Ro-Ru, 2014 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Sa-Sn, 2014 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - So-Sw, 2014 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - T, 2014 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - U-V, 2014 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Wa-Wh, 2014 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Wi-Wr, 2014 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Y-Z, 2014 (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Unidentified, 2014 (Box 18, Folder 9)